<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-01-13T12:52:43-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">VA Big Data Genomics Blog</title><subtitle>Designing cloud based solutions to manage and analyze big genomic data.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Paul’s monthly roundup: January 2023</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/01/13/paul-roundup-january.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paul’s monthly roundup: January 2023" /><published>2023-01-13T10:10:02-08:00</published><updated>2023-01-13T10:10:02-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/01/13/paul-roundup-january</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/01/13/paul-roundup-january.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;happy-new-year&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Happy new year!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By my count, I’ve created and presented over 90 slide decks in this group alone. So, with a new year we are going to mix it up and try a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/va-big-data-genomics/general-practices/blob/main/group-meetings.md&quot;&gt;new meeting structure&lt;/a&gt;! We are all remote, don’t bother containing your excitement. Instead of presenting slide decks, updates will be provided in the form of written reports like this, so that the bulk of the meeting can be dedicated to discussion. Rather than writing an entire document for each meeting, the idea is that group members will be continually creating documentation in the form of Jupyter notebooks and markdown documents as well as GitHub commits, pull requests, and issues. This report will be act as a summary of all those activities to provide some context and a narrative throughline for readers. Now, let’s get to the rest of the updates!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://med.stanford.edu/gbsc/projects/vapahcs/_jcr_content/sidebar-top/panel_builder_919821219/panel_0/accordion/accordion_content1/image.img.320.high.jpg/joseph-sarro.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Congratulations to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/joseph-sarro-m-s-ph-d-61422b6b/&quot;&gt;Joe Sarro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, who was our outstanding performer of 2022. Joe joined us at the beginning of 2022 and immediately hit the ground running learning a slew of new technologies and science related to whole genome sequencing. He expanded and improved the aggregation and quality control pipeline pioneered by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/jina-song-55820827/&quot;&gt;Jina Song&lt;/a&gt; and then took the lead in expanding our aggregation capability by an order of magnitude. He’s now putting the finishes touches on a dataset of over 100,000 whole genomes that we are excited to release in early 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New blog&lt;/strong&gt; Meeting updates will be posted on our new &lt;a href=&quot;https://va-big-data-genomics.github.io/&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;, hosted on GitHub Pages. This is it! You are on it! Wow. It uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; to generate the site, which means we can write all the content in &lt;strong&gt;markdown&lt;/strong&gt;. This is great because 1) nobody has to learn HTML or Javascript and 2) content generated for the blog can be easily translated to other mediums (PDFs, slide decks, other sites). You can find the source repository &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/va-big-data-genomics/va-big-data-genomics.github.io&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Check out this &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/va-big-data-genomics/va-big-data-genomics.github.io/issues/1&quot;&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt; if you are interested in the trials and tribulations I went through to get it live. It actually wasn’t that bad, but it did reinforce my opinion of Ruby as the worst programming language.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New post&lt;/strong&gt; To celebrate the launch of our new blog, I wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://va-big-data-genomics.github.io/jekyll/update/2023/01/12/infrastructure-lessons-from-pbot.html&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; examining the physical infrastructure challenges of my local Portland Bureau of Transportation and what lessons from them we can apply to building and maintaining digital infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2022: Exploration&lt;/strong&gt; Last year we spent a lot of time exploring methods for storing, sharing, and using information: GitHub, Jupyter notebooks, markdown, presentation methods.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2023: Structure&lt;/strong&gt; This year, I want to distill the knowledge we gained last year and start applying structure to it in terms of standard practices and specifications.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/va-big-data-genomics&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; as our primary information repository&lt;/strong&gt; In the past, we’ve split information between Google Drive and GitHub, and Drive was mostly used for slide decks. In transitioning away from slide deck presentations, I think we can also move away from Drive.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lessons from Amazon&lt;/strong&gt; The new meeting structure is partly inspired by a 2020, Kristen Bahler article describing what goes on “&lt;a href=&quot;https://money.com/amazon-meetings-no-powerpoint/&quot;&gt;Inside Amazon’s Very Weird (But Very Efficient) Staff Meetings&lt;/a&gt;” at published on money.com. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/daniel-cotter-45762096/&quot;&gt;Daniel&lt;/a&gt; brought up their meeting style months ago and I was initially skeptical of it, mainly because of the 6 page document, but now I’m more amenable . Here’s some things I liked and didn’t like from the article.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;What I like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fostering a “culture of writing”. I’m firmly of the view that writing is the best way to capture and distribute knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Getting more people involved in discussions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;No PowerPoint&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;What I didn’t like:&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Writing a 6 page document for single use in a meeting. My goal for documentation is that it becomes integrated with everyone’s daily workflow, rather than being a separate burdensome task.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turn your camera off&lt;/strong&gt; An &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0247655&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; published in PLOS ONE indicates that turning your camera off might improve communication during teleconferencing. Let’s try it!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Billing-Ross</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Happy new year!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sustaining bioinformatics infrastructure: lessons from PBOT</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/01/12/infrastructure-lessons-from-pbot.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sustaining bioinformatics infrastructure: lessons from PBOT" /><published>2023-01-12T15:10:02-08:00</published><updated>2023-01-12T15:10:02-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/01/12/infrastructure-lessons-from-pbot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2023/01/12/infrastructure-lessons-from-pbot.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1590866249433-0310439fdab9?ixlib=rb-4.0.3&amp;amp;ixid=MnwxMjA3fDB8MHxwaG90by1wYWdlfHx8fGVufDB8fHx8&amp;amp;auto=format&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;w=1170&amp;amp;q=80&quot; alt=&quot;Hawthorne Bridge in Portland&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;font size=&quot;3&quot;&gt;
Photo of the Hawthorne Bridge in Portland by Ryan Manwiller on &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/he5iQ3hgbv8&quot;&gt;Unsplash&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/font&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our group is responsible for building and maintaining robust cloud based infrastructure to manage, process, and analyze large scale genomic datasets. As a small group in a rapidly evolving field, we are under constant pressure to expand our offerings and generate new datasets. Our challenge is to establish a framework for adding new features while also sustaining existing ones, all while the size of our datasets gets steadily larger. By taking lessons from physical systems, we can learn to better manage our digital ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;focus-on-the-process&quot;&gt;Focus on The Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the internal and external pressure on our group is in regards to generating data, because our stakeholders need data to generate results, and all of the incentives in academia are structured around results. Nobody awards grants for maintenance. It’s tempting to conform to these pressures and choose the shortest path towards generating data and getting results. However, the shortest path to results is to forego establishing robust, well documented, reproducible methods; which is why so much scientific research is not reproducible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/533452a&quot;&gt;crisis&lt;/a&gt;” of reproducibility is an abstract one for most researchers, it is of immediate concern to us because our job is to repeat these methods to generate larger and larger datasets ad infinitum. And the bigger the data, the greater the strain on the scalability of our methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-4-billion-backlog&quot;&gt;A $4 billion backlog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t build roads but we do build infrastructure, and when I think of the importance of building and maintaining robust infrastructure, I think of my local Portland Bureau of Transportation (PBOT). PBOT currently has a &lt;a href=&quot;https://bikeportland.org/2022/11/02/whats-behind-pbots-4-4-billion-street-maintenance-backlog-excuse-366371&quot;&gt;$4.4 billion maintenance backlog&lt;/a&gt;. This has all kinds of negative consequences:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rejection of new projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Frustration of PBOT workers who can’t address problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Frustration of residents who want good infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And every year the maintenance issues go unresolved, the burden of using their infrastructure increases, as does the cost of fixing it, creating a negative feedback loop that will take massive investment to resolve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-did-they-get-there&quot;&gt;How did they get there?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it didn’t take long. In 2005, the maintenance backlog only amounted to $28 million. Official site multiple causes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inadequate maintenance funds for expensive infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lack of political will: maintenance isn’t sexy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bigger and heavier vehicles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Federal grant programs don’t pay for maintenance (Hello, NIH!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How are they going to fix it? Not easily and not soon. So, what lessons can we translate to bioinformatics infrastructure?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;lessons-for-bioinformatics&quot;&gt;Lessons for bioinformatics&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on maintaining existing systems from the outset. Once you get into a hole, it’s difficult to get out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Regulate usage of your infrastructure to sustainable methods. Less repeatable means more expensive to maintain.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Budget maintenance into your capacity for projects and assume that every resource requires maintenance to address things like bigger datasets, new types of data, software updates, and cloud platform updates.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Measure the time you are spending on each project. How does actual time spent match your expectations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;establish-a-strategy-and-specifications&quot;&gt;Establish a Strategy and Specifications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expanding features and services with minimal labor cost is a significant challenge. Another, more positive example from PBOT demonstrates a strategy for doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the projects that has been hamstrung by PBOT’s budget woes is the expansion of bike lanes. But, in 2022, they got a new section of &lt;a href=&quot;https://bikeportland.org/2022/10/28/a-global-corporation-paid-for-and-built-protected-bike-lanes-on-nw-front-ave-366380&quot;&gt;bike lanes&lt;/a&gt; built at no cost to the city. How did they do it? They didn’t. They provided specifications for the bike lanes and a local corporation hired contracts to install them near their headquarters. Why they did it somewhat questionable (people had been parking RVs along that strip of road), but ethics aside, the city got new infrastructure at no cost. Again, how does this apply to digital infrastructure?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;publish-specifications-for-extending-infrastructure&quot;&gt;Publish specifications for extending infrastructure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If others want to extend our infrastructure with new algorithms or features, let them. Ideally, provide tutorials for development, testing, and validation. Just make sure their additions meet the specifications you have established. Introducing variability into the system will make it more complicated and harder to maintain. Can you write automated tests to validate that new features meet specifications? Teach people to fish, rather than giving them fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;establish-a-strategy-for-expanding-infrastructure&quot;&gt;Establish a strategy for expanding infrastructure&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new bike lanes weren’t placed arbitrarily, they were added in accordance with PBOT’s Bicycle Plan for 2030, an overarching plan that includes a map of bike lanes intended to be added over a 20 year period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When PBOT, an institution tasked with advancing the public good, adds a bike lane they aren’t just creating a path; they are indicating to the public that they should bike there. It signals to the public that “We experts have studied traffic patterns and added this path because it is optimal route for cycling to some place.” If people use the path and find that it is not an ideal route, it erodes public confidence in the entire institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a data generator, our goal is to provide high quality datasets to all researchers in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.research.va.gov/mvp&quot;&gt;Million Veteran Program&lt;/a&gt;. By adding infrastructure to generate a new dataset for researchers, we are tacitly endorsing that dataset; that we have vetted the algorithm that generated it, validated the results, and are confident in the quality of the data. By performing this due diligence we allow researchers to focus on analyzing the data rather than validating it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By adhering to these principles, we can transition from research-grade to enterprise-grade infrastructure, and establish a foundation that will support new features and ever expanding data.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Billing-Ross</name></author><category term="jekyll" /><category term="update" /><summary type="html">Photo of the Hawthorne Bridge in Portland by Ryan Manwiller on Unsplash.</summary></entry></feed>